now we will see how Loop unrolling Works
suppose we have this Loop in the C
language where I goes from 1,000 down to
zero and in each iteration of the loop
we add something to the E element of the
array a when we translate this into
instructions we get a loop like the one
we have already seen we load from the
array element so R1 is now the pointer
to the E element of the array we load
that we add R3 that would be r s to that
and then we store it back into the A ofi
and then we move our pointer four places
down that's equivalent to decrementing I
and then we check whether the pointer
has reached the beginning of the array
which is equivalent to checking whether
I is zero now let's apply Loop and
rolling to this Loop we will do what we
call unrolling once we unroll the loop
by making each iteration of the new Loop
do more than one iteration of the old
Loop so when we unroll once what we want
to do is now each iteration of the new
Loop will be doing the work that it
should be doing plus the work of the
next iteration however if we just do it
this way then we're doing the same work
twice so instead what we will do is we
will adjust the index so that this is
doing the E element of the array and
then I would be decremented and the next
iteration would now do a of IUS
one however this Loop still
counts one at a time so we do this we
add s to the next element in the next
iteration of the loop we would now add s
again to the same element we already
processed here so we also need to adjust
the loop counter update to update by two
now and now we have a new Loop that has
half as many iterations Each of which is
doing the work of the two original
iterations we could unroll the loop more
than once for example unrolling two
times would mean that this Loop is doing
now three times the work of the original
iteration for this once unrolled Loop
the instructions would look like this we
would have the actual work of the one
iteration these are the same
instructions as here we now want to do
this work once more this would be this
however if we just copied the
instructions again we would be doing the
same work twice we would just add our
three again to our same element a ofi so
instead we will adjust the offset here
so that we are accessing the element
right below the one that R1 is pointing
to this would be the a of I minus one
and now we need our Loop counter update
and the actual loop back branch but
those we cannot simply copy just like
here we had to update the counter to
count by two iterations in this code we
were decrementing R1 to move to the
element below now we're processing two
elements at a time so we need to move 8
bytes at a time so the approach to
unrolling Once is take the original work
copy it twice adjust a second copy so
that it does the second iterations worth
of work and then adjust the loop count
so that it's moving by two iterations
not by one this is what it means to
unroll once so keep in mind that when we
are doing two iterations at a time we
have unrolled the loop once because we
have added one iteration of the original
Loop in addition to what the iteration
normally would be doing unrolling twice
would mean that we are doing three
iterations at a time unrolling three
times means that we are doing four times
the work and so on
it is a very common mistake that when
you're asked to unroll the loop twice
unroll it this way this is unrolling
only once again unrolling twice is not
do two iterations at a time it's do one
plus two iterations at a time because
you always have to do one iteration so
this Loop is not unrolled once it is not
unrolled at all this is unrolled once